PROFESSOR: Today we're going
to continue talking about
Markov decision processes.
Our running example was grid world.
And grid world was basically
an agent stuck in a maze.
There were squares, and the agent
was in some square in the grid.
And there were walls that you
couldn't move through.
The main thing about grid world is
that the movement was noisy.
That is, we didn't really know
the outcome of an action.
So an action like north probably would
move you one square north,
but it might not.
So 80% of the time, you go where you
expect, and 10% of the time, you
either go west or east, if you're
trying to go north.
You'll never actually go south.
And that was important in some of the
weird edge cases that we saw.
Any movement that would have put
you into a wall instead leaves
you where you are.
The other thing about grid world, in
addition to the fact that the actions
were non-deterministic, is that there
were rewards at each timestep.
There are two kinds of rewards
in grid world.
This is just one of many, many MDPs.
In this particular MDP, the big
rewards come at the end when
you exit the grid.
And in this particular grid, you either
get a plus 1 or a minus 1,
depending on which exit you take.
And there's also a living reward
that you receive each step.
And that living reward could
be zero, it could be
positive, it could be negative.
This distinction between big rewards
at the end and a living
reward along the way--
this is the reward structure for grid
world, not for MDPs in general.
The goal of an agent in an MDP is
to maximize its sum of rewards.
And there was one tricky part, which
was we had this notion of discount,
that if we chose, we could set rewards
in the future to be worth less than
rewards in the present.
And that was a factor gamma that could
be anywhere between zero and one.
There were a bunch of important
quantities in MDPs.
Most of them line up to something we
know from search or from Expectimax.
But it's very important that we keep
these quantities straight, because
some of them are very
subtly different.
And especially today we're going
to see lots of subtle
variations of these things.
These quantities are also important
because we'll need them next week for
reinforcement learning.
So let's make sure we're totally
clear on what these things are.
For the Markov decision process itself,
whenever you see an MDP you
think non-deterministic
search problem.
So just like a search problem,
it's got states.
It's got actions that you can
take in those states.
And the critical new bit is
the transition function.
And this is important.
We're going to be seeing the transition
function in equations all
over today.
The transition function tells
you what your actions do.
That is, for any state s and action a,
the transition function looks at an
outcome, s-prime, and it tells you
whether it's possible, meaning its
probability is non-zero, and if it's
possible, how likely it is.
And that's the probability of s-prime,
the outcome state, given your action.
And we write that as
T of s, a, s-prime.
Whenever you see T of s, a, s-prime, you
think, oh, that's the probability
of landing in s-prime.
Similarly, each transition from s, a to
s-prime comes along with a reward
that is part of the definition
of the MDP.
These rewards can be positive,
they can be negative.
And in addition to having a reward each
timestep, there's also a discount
gamma that tells you whether or not
the future rewards are worth less.
There's also a start state.
So what are the quantities?
Some of the quantities are pretty
straightforward, because we've had
them around for a while.
So for example, there's
a notion of a policy.
A policy is a map of
states to actions.
You can think of it as a lookup
table, and sometimes it is.
It takes a state and it
tells you what to do.
Of course, there's good policies and
bad policies, And we'll think about
that idea today.
There's this notion of the utility.
The utility for the agent is more or
less the sum of the rewards it gets.
So each timestep, you get a reward.
But the utility is over
an entire sequence.
It's more or less the sum, but future
rewards may be discounted.
Now a critical difference is between the
utility of a sequence of rewards,
or to a first approximation you add
them up, and the value of a state.
The value of a state is what you expect
your future utility to be under
optimal action.
So remember that.
When we talk about the value of the
state, it's not the next reward you're
going to receive.
It's not a certain number--
I know I'm going to get 10 points--
because you don't know what your
actions will do.
This is an average outcome
under optimal action.
And whenever you think about that
average outcome over optimal action,
what should pop into your head is an
Expectimax tree that looks like this.
And what you want to think about is,
well, from any given state s, what is
this notion of a value?
It's not what I'm definitely
going to achieve.
It can't be that, because I don't
control my actions perfectly.
What it is is it's the average outcome
under optimal action, meaning
essentially I do Expectimax
computations.
I think, when I have an action that I
control, I'm going to take a max.
And whenever I hit a chance node in my
evaluation of this tree, I'm going to
have to take an average of the children,
where the weights and the
average are the transition function.
So when you see value, you think, oh,
that's what Expectimax gives if I run
it from a state.
It's an Expectimax value.
The critical other quantity
that's new is a Q-value.
What's a Q-value?
It's just like a value.
It is what you would get in an
Expectimax tree if you ran the
Expectimax computation--
that is, maxing when you max and
averaging when you average.
The difference is values are what you
get when you ask, what happens from
this state?
Well, I choose the best action and
something happens, then I choose the
best action.
That's Expectimax.
So this is values here.
That's V. Q-values, Q, are what
you get at a chance node.
At a chance node, it's too late
to change the action a
that you just took.
A chance node is a state and you've
committed to an action.
The first thing that's going to
happen from a chance node is
the action will resolve.
Who knows what will happen?
Your transition function tells
you what the likelihoods are.
But whenever you see a Q-value, you
think, oh, that's what Expectimax
would give if I started it at a chance
node, meaning first it would average
and then thereafter it would
take maximal actions.
When we think about an MDP,
we think about optimal
quantities most of the time.
So in general, we want to know for a
state what is the optimal value?
That is, what is the value
if I act optimally?
I take all the right decisions, and then
I average over the things that
are out of my control.
Whenever I mean something optimal
and I want to be explicit, I
add this star here.
This star is always going
to mean optimal for us.
So V* is the value that we get starting
in s and acting optimally.
That's just what Expectimax computes.
Q* is the value of the Q-state
acting optimally.
Again, same thing.
Just what Expectimax computes.
Finally, there are many policies.
Some are good, some are bad.
An optimal policy can
be written as pi*.
A lot of what we do with MDPs is we
take in the problem specification,
which has transitions and rewards and
discounts, and we compute various
quantities like this.
Sometimes we're interested in the
values, but usually we're interested
in the policies.
Just like before, when we did, say,
min, max, or Expectimax, we had an
algorithm for computing the values.
The reason that we ran this algorithm
was because we wanted to use it to
figure out the policies.
And so at the very top of the
computation, you do something special
to figure out which policy gave
rise to that optimal value.
Let's take a look at what the values
look like in grid world.
So here is a grid world.
Remember, grid world has
lots of parameters.
In addition to the maze layout,
we can vary the discount.
We can vary the living penalty.
And as we vary these things, the shape
of the policy and the values
are going to change.
We saw last time that for some values
of the living reward, you're very
cautious and take your time.
For other values, you jump
straight into the pit.
And in between, you get other
kinds of actions.
Here's one particular setting.
And the important point here is what
you're looking at is values.
The numbers here are the values.
And that is that if you are in this
square, where the only action
available to you is exit--
upon which you immediately receive
a reward of plus 1--
your value is plus 1.
Down here, in the start state in the
lower left, your value is 0.49.
What's that mean?
You're not usually going to get 0.49.
Sometimes you're going to get more.
Sometimes you're going to get less.
This is the long-term average
you're going to get.
And that average bakes
in a lot of things.
It bakes in the fact that you're going
to get a small penalty each step until
you get to the exit.
And if your actions mess up, you
might get that penalty more.
It bakes in the fact that the plus 1 is
far away, and by the time you get
there it will be discounted.
It bakes in all of the probabilities
in the transition function.
All of that's in the value.
If you act optimally, you'll get
0.49 as your average score.
Now what do I mean by act optimally?
Well, the optimal policy for this
particular setting is also shown.
That's these arrows.
So when you look at these arrows,
they're basically a lookup table.
From this state, take
the action north.
It doesn't mean you're
going to go north.
You'll probably go north,
but you might not.
You might slip.
From this square here-- this is the
interesting tricky square, where
you're on the ledge between
the wall and the pit--
it says go north.
And with some probability, yeah, you're
going to fall in the pit.
But for these particular settings,
that's the risk you take in the
optimal policy.
So here you see a policy and values.
What about Q-values?
What do those look like?
There's a value for every state.
There's a Q-value for every
state/action pair.
And for each of these states,
there are four actions.
So here they are.
So let's look at the tricky case.
It's the interesting one.
That's the square here, where you're
between the wall and the pit.
And what you can see here
is for the action east--
so the Q-state being on the
ledge and going east--
the Q-value is pretty low.
It's an optimal Q-value, but it
represents being committed to going
east, so you're in that chance node,
and then acting optimally.
Well, you can only do so much
from there, so the value is
low for that Q-state.
The value for the Q-state going north,
which you'll remember was the optimal
action from this state, is 0.57,
which was the value of that
state to begin with.
So this is what Q-values look like.
They're kind of like values but
partitioned, where there's a value for
each action.
And that's nice, because among other
things, you can tell which option was
good by looking at the Q-values
and comparing them.
A very important point about
these values and rewards.
Rewards are for one timestep.
Values are from that point forward until
the end of the game, or forever
if the game doesn't end.
Rewards are instantaneous.
Values are cumulative.
It's a very important distinction.